Okay today's דף *daf* is ק"ו *kuf vav* מנחות menachos, *Menachot* 106.
We're actually ahead, we pick up on ק"ו עמוד א' *kuf vav
amud alef* about halfway down, maybe even a little more than halfway,
by the two dots פירשתי מנחה mincha של עשרונים *Perashti minchah shel
esronim*. Okay I designated a מנחה mincha *minchah* of עשרונים *esronim* and
because so you bring sixty because that's the most you could have
meant and you stipulate what's my נדר neder *neder* my נדר neder,
*neder* the rest is free will, but here because it's a מנחה
mincha *minchah* singular of עשרונים *esronim* then it has to be one
מנחה mincha, *minchah* of X עשרונים *esronim*. רבי Rebbe *Rebbi* says well
then it has to be the exact amount and you need to
bring every amount 1 2 3 4 5 up to 60 because
it has to be exactly what you said. Okay let's take a
look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan, *Tanu Rabanan*
rabbis taught פירשתי מנחה mincha וקבעתי בכלי אחד bikeli echad, *Perashti minchah
v'kavati b'kli echad* so I set a מנחה mincha? *minchah* and I
said in one vessel, right our משנה Mishna *mishna* you didn't say
in one vessel but somehow that's understood to be what you mean
when you say a מנחה mincha *minchah* a singular מנחה mincha *minchah*.
Okay פירשתי מנחה mincha, וקבעתי בכלי אחד *Perashti minchah v'kavati b'kli echad*
של עשרונים *shel esronim* of עשרונים *esronim* right because before also we
discussed the possibility of bringing a מנחה mincha, *minchah* in multiple vessels
and so on. Okay so here you were either explicit or it's
implicit one vessel of עשרונים *esronim* ואיני יודע מה פירשתי *v'eini yodeia
mah perashti* and I don't know how many עשרונים *esronim* I said.
יביא מנחה mincha של ששים עשרונים דברי חכמים chachamim *yavi minchah she-shishim
esronim Divrei Chachamim* you bring sixty and you stipulate what's needed for
my נדר neder. *neder* is נדר neder *neder* and the rest is
a נדבה nedava? *nedavah* is an additional מנחה mincha *minchah* free will.
רבי אומר Rabbi omer יביא מנחות menachot של עשרונים מאחד ועד ששים
*Rebbi omer yavi menachot shel esronim me-echad v'ad shishim* you bring from
1 to 60 presumably the guy feels that he could have said
עשרון isaron *issaron* in the singular as well. Okay so you bring
all the options from 1 to 60 שהן *she-hen* which is how
much is the total? 1 2 3 4 what do you do
when you add all the numbers from 1 to 60?
1830.
How do you get this? Well you could obviously add it but
there's a trick and here's the trick. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* tells you
the trick. This works for any sequence of number. Basically imagine you
have in front of you a line of numbers 1 through 60.
You take the one at the beginning and the end. A 1
and a 60 is 61. Then the next two numbers 2 and
a 59 61. The next two numbers 3 and 58 61. Okay
how many sets of 61 do you have? Well what's your last
set? 30 and 31. Okay so therefore you have thirty sets 1
through 30 and all of the matching it's like a string that's
folded over. So it is 30 times 61 and 30 times 61
is do the math 1830.
So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* has that brilliant trick if you look at
תוספות Tosfos. שהן אלף ושמונה מאות ושלשים כיצד קח בידך מאחד ועד
ששים וצרף תחילתן וסופן עד האמצע כגון אחד וששים הן ששים ואחד
*Tosafot she-hen elef u-shmoneh me'ot u-shloshim keitzad kach b'yadcha me-echad v'ad shishim
v'tzaref techilatan v'sofan ad ha-emtza k'gon echad v'shishim hen shishim v'echad* 1
and 60 61 2 and 59 61. So תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* has
the entire trick. Now if you go look at the web you
will find out under Carl Gauss he lived from like 1777 to
1850 something that he a brilliant mathematician and apparently the legend is
that he realized this as a young boy that the teacher tried
to keep him busy and told him to add up all the
numbers from whatever it was I think 1 to 100 and he
came up with the answer in a few seconds because he realized
this trick. So this trick is attributed to him but actually somebody
needed to have said that it was at least 500 years before
him in this תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* but maybe the point is that
he was the first one to ever think of it but he
realized it as a small boy. Anyway there is the trick. Okay
so that's רבי Rebbe *Rebbi* 1830. פירשתי ואיני יודע מה פירשתי pirashti
ve-eini yode-a mah pirashti, ואיזו מהם פירשתי *Perashti v'eini yodeia mah perashti
v'eizo mehem perashti* I set exactly how much but I don't know
how many and I don't know which type of מנחה mincha *minchah*
so there are five types. So now you're going to have to
multiply it by five. ואיזו מהם פירשתי ואיני יודע כמה kamah? פירשתי
*v'eizo mehem perashti v'eini yodeia kamah perashti*.
Actually there's like an extra phrase here the side tries to take
it out. It's איני יודע מה פירשתי ואיזו מהם פירשתי ואיני יודע
כמה פירשתי *eini yodeia mah perashti v'eizo mehem perashti v'eini yodeia kamah
perashti*. So כמה פירשתי *kamah perashti* is how big. איזו מהם *eizo
mehem* is what type. So מה פירשתי *mah perashti* might just be
the global. I don't know what I said meaning I don't know
what I said in terms of how many and what type. Okay
but anyway that's the additional question what type and how much. So
יביא חמש מנחות menachot של ששים עשרונים דברי חכמים chachamim, *yavi chamesh
menachot she-shishim esronim Divrei Chachamim*. So חכמים *Chachamim* say so fine you
have to bring sixty of each different type because you might have
you don't know which type you meant and within each type you
don't know if you meant any number from 1 to 60 but
you can bring 60 in each and stipulate the right amount is
for your נדר neder, *neder* everything else is the right type and
the right amount within that type is your נדר neder *neder* and
everything else is a נדבה nedava, *nedavah*. But for רבי Rebbe *Rebbi*
every single it has to be the exact amount per כלי kli
*kli*. So רבי Rebbi אומר יביא חמש מנחות Minchos של ששים עשרונים
מאחד ועד ששים *Rebbi omer yavi chamesh menachot she-shishim esronim me-echad v'ad
shishim* so you have to go 1 to 60 and then you
multiply by 5. So if before we had 1830 times 5 do
the math 1800 times 5 is 9000 30 times 5 150 9150
שהם תשעת אלפים ומאה וחמשים *she-hem tishat alafim u-me'ah va-chamishim*.
Okay very nice. Now that we're done with that math let's try
to get at the heart of the debate. במאי קמיפלגי bemai kamifligi,
*b'mai kamifligi* what is this debate about like what is the question
why Why for רבי Rebbi can't you just say the X amount
in the כלי kli is my נדר neder and the rest is
my נדבה? nedava, Even if it has to all be בכלי אחד,
you said it was all going to be in one vessel and
you can't have the option the גמרא Gemara said yesterday, have sixty
and sixty different vessels, one עשרון issaron per vessel in sixty different.
You said that the total amount has to be in one vessel.
Fine, but why can't you add to it and put in and
have sixty? The full amount is in one vessel and if there's
anything extra, well that's a
נדר, neder that's a נדבה, nedava. free-will מנחה mincha, that's being put
in the same vessel with the נדר. neder Why not? Why does
רבי Rebbi resist having it possibly contain more? So במאי קמיפלגי, what's
the debate about? אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda במותר להכניס חולין
לעזרה קמיפלגי, bemuttar lehachnis chullin la'azarah kamifligi,
that the extra amount we're going to say is not a נדבה,
nedava. which is strange. It would seem like you never want to
bring something non-sanctified and you're going to have to put it up
on the מזבח mizbe'ach and whatnot. But for right now the גמרא
Gemara is going to assume that actually it's easier if the extra
amount that's not needed is חולין, chullin, is not
sanctified. Okay. And then the question is, can you bring in a
vessel that might contain a part of it being חולין? chullin? במותר
להכניס חולין לעזרה קמיפלגי. bemuttar lehachnis chullin la'azarah kamifligi. רבי סבר Rebbe
savar אסור להכניס חולין לעזרה, assur lehachnis chullin la'azarah,
you can't. And therefore you have to have each one in its
separate vessel. So each one in its separate vessel, you can just
say the one that I'm sanctifying as my נדר neder is my
נדר, neder everything else I'm sanctifying as a נדבה. nedava? But for
some reason and we'll understand better in a few minutes, we're assuming
that when you have to put more in the same vessel, sixty,
and some of it is נדר neder, and some of it is
extra, that there's specifically a reason that you don't want that to
be a נדבה. nedava So what we're going to assume we're going
to want that to be, if for that's how we're going to
make it operate, is going to be חולין. chullin. So רבי Rebbi's
is going to say if that's what you have to do, put
חולין chullin in together with your נדר neder because again some of
it might be חולין, chullin, then that you can't do. You can't
bring that into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. אסור להכניס חולין לעזרה.
assur lehachnis chullin la'azarah. ורבנן סברי V'rabbanan savri מותר להכניס חולין לעזרה.
muttar lehachnis chullin la'azarah. Now that's funny because normally everybody agrees you
can't bring חולין לעזרה. chullin la'azarah. And also here, you're going to
have to do stuff, you're going to have to take a קומץ,
kometz, you're going to have to burn it on the מזבח mizbe'ach
or what, I mean you're going to have to treat it like
a קרבן. korban. So it really is a problem. So that's very
hard to understand and it's hard to understand why the גמרא Gemara
thinks that חולין chullin is going to be better here. Why don't
you just make the rest a נדבה? nedava. So let's take a
look. רבא אמר Rava amar דכולי עלמא dechulei alma אסור להכניס חולין
לעזרה. assur lehachnis chullin la'azarah.
No no no, obviously you can't be חולין. chullin. והכא במותר לערב
חובה בנדבה קמיפלגי. Vehacha bemuttar le'arev chovah binedava kamifligi. That's it. For
some reason we thought it was easier to mix חולין chullin with
your חובה, chovah, but now we're saying no no no, nobody wants
חולין chullin here. So the question is fine, so then you're going
to mix חובה, chovah, your obligatory, the vow you took, with an
extra, with a נדבה nedava because you're going to sanctify whatever in
that sixty is not my נדר neder is a נדבה. nedava And
that's the issue, are you allowed to mix those two together? Again,
interesting that the גמרא Gemara seems that like it's easier to mix
חולין, chullin, it was more ready to go there with your חובה
chovah than it is your נדבה nedava, with your חובה. chovah. רבנן
סברי Rabbanan savri מותר לערב חובה בנדבה, muttar le'arev chovah binedava, רבי
סבר Rebbe savar אסור לערב חובה בנדבה. assur le'arev chovah binedava. That's
the debate. Okay.
So
now
probably what you're thinking is according to either scenario, what we haven't
dealt with yet is if you've got a mixture and it all
might be one מנחה mincha and it might be multiple מנחות, how
are you going to take your קומץ? kometz? Do you need one
קומץ kometz or do you need two קמצים? kematzim?
And maybe that's why the גמרא Gemara preferred it to be חולין,
chullin, because if it's חולין, chullin, then there's here in this כלי
kli. of sixty, there's only one קרבן. korban. You don't know how
much is a קרבן korban and how much is חולין, chullin, but
there's only one קרבן, korban, so you only need to take one
קומץ. kometz. But now that we've got a נדר neder, and a
נדבה nedava mixed in the same, which the רבנן Rabbanan are okay
with and רבי Rebbi is not, like you don't know, is it
one קומץ kometz because it's a sixty, maybe your נדר neder was
sixty, maybe it's two קמצים? kematzim? And also, won't your קומץ kometz
have a mixture of some of the נדר neder and some of
the
נדבה, nedavah, flour like מנחה mincha, in it? How do you know
which one you're taking it from? So that's really what the גמרא
Gemara is now going to turn itself to. אמר ליה אביי לרבא
Amar lei Abaye le'Rava לרבנן דאמרי מותר לערב חובה בנדבה, le'Rabbanan de'amri
muttar le'arev chovah binedava, so now you have a חובה chovah and
נדבה nedavah mixed together and they're going to require שני קמצים, sheni
kematzim, which is what makes it more complicated than בחולין bechullin and
the חובה. chovah. So לערב חובה בנדבה, le'arev chovah binedava, הא בעינן
שני קמצים, ha ba'inan sheni kematzim,
so you need to take two קמצים. kematzim. I mean it might
be one, it might be two, you don't know. So the גמרא
Gemara says דקמיץ והדר קמיץ, dekometz vehadar kometz, fine, so you take
two קמצים. kematzim. But now we've got a problem, maybe it's only
one.
And before we get to that, the קומץ kometz you took
is from some mix of the whole
מנחה, mincha you don't know, is it coming from the חובה chovah
part of the מנחה mincha or from the it might be not
the full amount from the חובה chovah part of
the
מנחה? mincha So the
גמרא Gemara says והא קמיץ מחובה אנדבה ומנדבה אחובה. veha kometz mechovah
anedava uminedava achovah. Each handbreadth has a mix. it's all in one
כלי. kli That's the whole point. So the גמרא Gemara says דתלי
ליה בדעת כהן. detali lei bedaat kohen. No, okay, that already you
can sort of say because, you know, if some is a חובה
chovah and some is a נדבה, nedavah. but you haven't segregated which
is which, so you can sort of stipulate
and
say it's going to be depend on what the כהן kohen takes
in his hand. And you say the following. כל היכא דמטיא ידיה
דכהן השתא חובה, kol heicha dematya yadeih dekohen hashta chovah,
wherever the כהן kohen sticks his hand now and takes the קומץ
kometz from, that section is the חובה. chovah. And now he's taking
all from the חובה. chovah. And now assuming that there's a נדבה
nedavah. here as well, that it's less than sixty that I said,
the next section that he sticks his hand in now and taking
the next קומץ kometz from, that section is the נדבה. nedavah. Okay
fine. השתא חובה ולבסוף נדבה hashta chovah ulevasof nedavah and then נדבה.
nedavah Okay fine.
So
now you got two קמצים kematzaim and if there were two, if
you did say less than sixty, each is a proper קומץ kometz
and you're going to burn them properly. But if you said sixty,
only one of them is a proper קומץ. kometz. There is no
נדבה. nedavah, So now you're going to burn some of the actual
קרבן korban as a, you know, what's the remnant of the מנחה
mincha you're going to burn it as if it were a קומץ.
kometz. You're not allowed to do that, that has to be eaten
by the כהנים. kohanim. So the גמרא Gemara says ואידך היכי מקטר
veidach heichi maktar
and how- so first it wants to figure out the order. What
order are you going to offer up the קומץ kometz in? ואידך
היכי מקטר. veidach heichi maktar. ליקטר נדבה ברישא liktar nedavah bereisha
first offer up the one that might be the, you know, that's
the נדבה nedavah that you can't do. דחובה היכי מקטר לה, dechovah
heichi maktar lah, how can then you then follow it with the
חובה? chovah? דילמא כולה חובה היא dilma kullah chovah hi when you
offer the one that you think is the נדבה, nedavah, that's if
you said less than sixty, then there actually is a נדבה nedavah
here. Okay, but if there wasn't, then you've just offered up a
קומץ kometz from part of the single
sixty עשרון isaron. מנחה mincha that you had. So היכי מקטר לה-
heichi maktar lah דילמא כולה חובה היא dilma kullah chovah hi maybe
the entire sixty is חובה chovah וחסרו להו שיריים. vechasru lehu shirayim.
And
when you offered that first קומץ kometz that
you thought maybe it's a נדבה, nedavah that's really taking some of
the non-קומץ kometz part of the מנחה, mincha okay, and burning it
up on the מזבח. mizbeach. ואמר מר שיריים שחסרו בין קמיצה להקטרה
אין מקטיר קומץ עליהם. veamar mar shirayim shechasru bein kemitzah lehaktarah ein
maktir kometz aleihem. So
if you're missing some of the שיריים shirayim after you took your
קמיצה kemitza but before you burned it, you can't burn the קומץ.
kometz. So what happens? You have this sixty thing here. You take
קומץ kometz number one and you put it in vessel number one
and that will be the חובה. chovah. קומץ kometz number two and
you put it in vessel number two and that will be the
נדבה nedavah assuming that there is a נדבה nedavah? part of this
sacrifice. So now, but you've already taken the קומץ. kometz. Now you
burn- if you were to burn number two first, well if there's
only
חובה, chovah, you've now taken the חובה, chovah, you've taken number one,
you took the קמיצה kemitza and now you burnt a part of
the שיריים, shirayim, number two, before you actually offered up the קומץ
kometz number one. That's not going to work. אין מקטיר קומץ
עליהם. ein maktir kometz aleihem. So ליקטר חובה ברישא liktar chovah bereisha
fine so do the obvious thing. Burn number one first and then
דנדבה היכי מקטיר ליה denedavah heichi maktir lei so now fine, you
burned number one for the חובה chovah you've fulfilled your obligation. Now
you have number two. In case there's a נדבה nedavah. in this
קרבן, korban, in this מנחה, mincha number two is its קומץ kometz
and you're going to burn it. Fine. But what if there's no
נדבה? nedava Then you're going to wind up burning the שיריים shirayim
of the קרבן. korban. היכי מקטר ליה, heichi maktir lei, how can
you burn it up? Top of קו עמוד ב. kuf vav amud
bet. ודילמא כולה חובה היא vedilma kullah chovah hi
maybe it's all a חובה chovah וכל שהוא ממנו לאישים הרי הוא
בבל תקטיר, vechol shehu mimenu leishim harei hu beval taktir, right? And
we know from a פסוק pasuk that says, you know, that we
learn out that anything
that you offer up onto the מזבח mizbeach ממנו לאישים mimenu leishim
from it goes onto the מזבח, mizbeach, any part of the remnant,
right? כי כל שאור וכל דבש לא תקטירו ממנו אשה להשם ki
kol seor vechol devash lo taktiru mimenu isheh l’Hashem it's a פסוק
pasuk about offering up yeast and honey. But we read it לא
תקטירו ממנו אשה להשם lo taktiru mimenu isheh l’Hashem anything that is
ממנו אשה להשם, mimenu isheh l’Hashem, any קרבן korban that from it
you offered it up on the fire, what is left over you
cannot offer on the fire. So there's an איסור issur to burn
the שיריים shirayim on the- offer it up on the מזבח. mizbeach.
So that number two, that thing that might be the קומץ kometz
of the נדבה. nedava, how can you burn it? That might be
the שירים shirayim of the חובה. chovah. There's maybe only a חובה
chovah here. So אמר רב יהודה בריה דרב שמעון בן פזי, Amar
Rav Yehuda brei d'Rav Shimon ben Pazi, so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
the son of רב שמעון בן פזי Rav Shimon ben Pazi said,
דמסיק להו לשום עצים, d'maseik lehu l'shum etzim, you put it up
on the מזבח mizbe'ach and treat it just as like fuel, firewood,
not as if you're doing it as a ritual burning of incense.
So like you stipulate. If there's a נדבה nedava. here, I said
less than sixty and part of this מנחה mincha is a נדבה,
nedava. this קומץ kometz is the קומץ kometz of the נדבה. nedava
And if I said sixty and the whole thing was my חובה,
chovah, then I'm just taking some of my מנחה mincha which should
be eaten by the כהנים kohanim and I'm using it as firewood,
but that's not the prohibition on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, but that's not
the prohibition of לא תקטירו lo taktiro because I'm not actually burning
it as an offering, I'm just burning it as fuel. Okay, וכדרבי
אליעזר, u'kh'Rabbi Eliezer, like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. דתניא רבי אליעזר אומר
לריח ניחוח אי אתה מעלה אבל אתה מעלה לשום עצים. D'tanya Rabbi
Eliezer omer l'reach nichoach ee atah ma'aleh aval atah ma'aleh l'shum etzim.
Okay, על המזבח לא יעלו לריח ניחוח. Al hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu l'reach
nichoach. When you're offering things like that that you're not allowed to
burn these things that are supposed to be eaten, that a piece
of them went on the מזבח mizbe'ach and you're not allowed to
offer the remainder up, you can't offer it up as a ריח
ניחוח reach nichoach as an offering, but you can put it up
on the fire as fuel. That's how you deal with these cases
of doubt. Okay, so that's how we've solved how it works for
the rabbis and for רבי Rebbi's says, I do not want you
mixing. We don't know exactly why not, but I don't want you
mixing two types and that's why you have to bring sixty separate
vessels. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי. Amar lei Rav
Acha brei d'Rava l'Rav Ashi. So רב אחא Rav Acha the son
of רבא Rava said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, ודילמא דכולי עלמא
מותר לערב חובה בנדבה. v'dilma d'kulei alma mutar l'arev chovah b'nedava. I
have a different way of explaining the debate. Maybe רבי Rabbi says
no in principle I'd be okay with you mixing חובה chovah and
נדבה. nedava והכא בדרבי אליעזר קמיפלגי. V'hacha b'd'Rabbi Eliezer kamiflagi. Maybe they're
debating this exact issue. Technically you could mix it, but is there
going to be a solution of being able to burn קומץ kometz
number two? Maybe we don't hold of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that
you can burn it as if it's firewood. דרבנן אית להו דרבי
אליעזר, Derabbanan it lehu d'Rabbi Eliezer, rabbis hold like רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer so you can burn קומץ kometz number two and say if
it's not working as a קומץ kometz because it's all a חובה
chovah then it should work as firewood. ורבי לית ליה דרבי אליעזר.
V'Rebbi leit lei d'Rabbi Eliezer. And רבי Rabbi doesn't hold of that
so maybe that's רבי's Rabbi problem, that there's no way of offering
up number two in a proper way. So אמר ליה, amar lei,
so he said back to him, no, אי סלקא דעתך לרבי מותר
לערב חובה בנדבה, ee salka dach'takh l'Rebbi mutar l'arev chovah b'nedava, if
רבי in principle held you could mix it together and it was
only a technical problem of how are you going to put up
the קומץ, kometz, that I could have a solution to. ודרבי אליעזר
לית ליה, v'd'Rabbi Eliezer leit lei, even if he wouldn't hold of
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, so how are you going to offer up
קומץ kometz number two? אפשר דמייתי שיתין בחד מנא. Efshar d'mayti shitin
b'chad mana. Here's what you do. You take sixty in one vessel,
and either X is your נדר, neder sixty minus X is your
נדבה nedava assuming, or it's all a נדר based on what you
said. וחד בחד מנא, v'chad b'chad mana, but you take one עישרון
issaron in another vessel. ומגע להו, u'maga lehu, and you have their
mouths, their up opening touching so there's a continuous amount of
flour running between the two at the top
surface. Okay, so it can function as one מנחה mincha, and here's
what you say. ומגע להו וקומץ, u'maga lehu v'kometz, and you take
a קמיצה. kmitza. So how do you take the קמיצה? kmitza? So
you take the first קמיצה kmitza from the big one of sixty
and that you're taking from your חובה. chovah. And then you say
the following: if I vowed sixty, that was the חובה, chovah, and
now this
separate עישרון issaron in this one vessel, that's a נדבה nedava and
you go take the קומץ kometz from that separate עישרון. issaron. Okay,
if however what I vowed was less than sixty, then what I'm
now giving as a נדבה nedava, is
everything that remains, sixty minus X in this first vessel plus what's
in the separate vessel, that's all my נדבה nedava and you still
take from the separate vessel. So basically the problem was that it
might have been sixty and then you're left with zero and you're
left with no נדבה, nedava so you might be offering up a
קומץ kometz of no נדבה nedava. and that's a problem. So what
you do is you ensure that there's going to be at least
some נדבה nedava here. You make it sixty-one. Okay, and that extra
one you take the קומץ kometz from and either it's going just
on that one or it's going on the one plus whatever is
left in the first כלי kli. and therefore you're definitely able to
offer up the קומץ kometz of a נדבה. nedava So that's a
very elegant solution. So that cannot be רבי's problem. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. רבא אמר, Rava amar, so one
explanation is they're arguing about mixing בין חולין בעזרה bein chullin b'azarah
which was strange. The other is whether you can mix חובה chovah
and נדבה nedava. without explaining why it should be a problem since
technically you can make it work as we've seen. רבא אמר דכולי
עלמא מותר לערב חובה בנדבה, Rava amar d'kulei alma mutar l'arev chovah
b'nedava, everybody says you could mix. וכולי עלמא אית להו דרבי אליעזר,
v'kulei alma it lehu d'Rabbi Eliezer, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer isn't
an issue and even if it were an issue we already said
there's a solution. והכא בפלוגתא דרבי אליעזר בן יעקב ורבנן קמיפלגי. vehacha
bepelugta deRabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov veRabbanan kamipalgi. There's another debate here, that
of רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov and the Rabbis,
and that's what's at the heart of this debate. דתנן detnan אפילו
מנחה של ששים עשרון afilu mincha shel shishim isaron נותן לה ששים
לוג. noten la shishim log. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov omer אפילו מנחה של ששים עשרון afilu mincha shel shishim
isaron אין לה אלא לוגה. ein la ela loga.
So you might remember this debate, right? The חכמים say it's always
proportional, one לוג log per עשרון. isaron, So if you bring sixty
עשרון, isaron, sixty לוג. log. Thirty עשרון, isaron, thirty לוג. log. רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says no matter how many
עשרונות isronot you bring, there's only one לוג log of oil per
מנחה, mincha שנאמר למנחה ולוג שמן. shenemar lamincha velog shemen. Whatever the
מנחה mincha is, one לוג log of oil. So now we really
understand the debate, okay? Because can you have, if you don't know
how many מנחות you've got, well if it's all one, so if
it's always the same proportion it doesn't matter. But if it's always
one לוג log per מנחה, mincha, then you don't know if in
this vessel of sixty do you have one מנחה mincha and one
לוג, log, or do you have two מנחות and two לוג. log.
Okay? So there's no way of doing everything in one vessel. That's
very brilliant that that just in terms of like what would create
a practical problem for doing it. Okay, so רבנן סברי כרבנן דאמרי
ששים לוג. Rabbanan savri keRabbanan de'amri shishim log. The Rabbis hold like
the Rabbis that say sixty for sixty. So you put sixty for
sixty. However much is sixty עשרון, sixty לוג. log. However much is
the נדר is the נדר, however much is the נדבה nedava is
the נדבה. nedava וכל חד וחד עשרון לוג קא שקיל. vechol chad
vechad isaron log ka shakil. And each מנחה mincha. the נדר gets
its proportion of לוגין lugin and the נדבה nedavah, gets its proportion
of לוגין. lugin. רבי סבר כרבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi savar keRabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov. But רבי holds like רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov דאמר אין לה אלא לוג. de'amar ein la ela
log. One לוג log no matter how big the מנחה mincha is.
ולא ידינן אי חדא מנחה היא. velo yadinan ei chada mincha hi.
So is this whole sixty thing one מנחה mincha דסגי לה בחד
לוג desagi la bechad log and then you're going to put one
לוג log of oil in it, אי שתי מנחות נינהו ei shtei
menachot ninhu or is it two דבעיין שתי לוגין deva'ayan shtei lugin
and you need two לוג. log. Okay, that's a very nice practical
reason why you can't have more than the base, each מנחה mincha,
has to be in its separate כלי. רב אשי אמר בקטן והביא
גדול קמיפלגי. Rav Ashi amar bekatan vehevi gadol kamipalgi. Now the question
is here when you have vowed an x amount, does is x
a minimum or is it the absolute amount? So if you say,
"When I said I'm obligating myself to bring a מנחה mincha of,"
you know, "three לוג," log, that you fulfill your obligation when you
bring thirty לוג. log. Okay, it's a minimum, you don't mean exactly
three לוג. log. So if that's true, even if you don't remember
what you said, bring sixty and you're definitely יוצא. yotzei. Okay, but
if you meant exact then you're not יוצא yotzei with sixty, and
then you need to bring separate ones. Okay? Why you can't mix
them for the reasons we said, the oil issue, the mixing issue,
but here assuming there's a problem with mixing it, you know, there's,
we've been assuming now that when you say x it means exactly
x. He says maybe their debate is whether you mean exactly x
or minimum x. All right, so let's take a look. רבנן סברי
קטן והביא גדול יצא, Rabbanan savri katan vehevi gadol yatza, that when
you said a small one and you bring a big one you're
יוצא. yotzei. So you're not even mixing, you're not even stipulating. You
said x, so you bring anything x or anything greater than x.
ורבי סבר לא יצא. veRabbi savar lo yatza. No, it's exactly what
you said, and therefore you would have to say this is a
mix of נדר and נדבה and that gets to all the problems
we said. So the גמרא Gemara says ומי פליגו בהא זימנא. umi
paligu beha zimna. But we already know that they debate that. דתנן,
detnan, we teach in a later משנה mishna. coming up, קטן והביא
גדול. katan vehevi gadol. You said that you're going to bring a
small animal and you bring a big one. יצא, yatza, you fulfill
your obligation. רבי אומר לא יצא, Rabbi omer lo yatza, you don't.
Now actually I've got to tell you that that's a much bigger
חידוש chiddush there according to the חכמים, right? Because a small animal
and a big animal are different animals. Okay, if I say three
and I bring ten, you know, it's the גמרא'ס Gemara's principle בכלל
מאתיים מנה, bechlal matayim mana, I'm also bringing three. All right? But
anyway, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. גמרא Gemara is
effectively going to say that. So the גמרא Gemara, says צריכא. tzricha.
No, you need to show the debate in both
places. דאי איתמר בהא בהא
קאמרי רבנן משום דאידי ואידי קומצו. de'i itmar beha beha qa'amri Rabbanan
mishum de'eidi ve'eidi qomzo. If you were would say it here, so
that if you say three you know you can bring a bigger
one, that's because at the end of the day what you're offering
on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, you know, is the same. Whether you're bringing
three or whether you're bringing thirty, it's one מנחה mincha. and one
קומץ kometz being offered on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So there it makes
sense that they could say that, you know, if you said three
it's also good if it's bigger. But in the case of an
animal, if you said a small animal, then it only has a
small amount of innards to put on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And if
you said a and when you bring a big one you're putting
a lot of innards on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. That's fundamentally a different
form of what you're offering up, you know, at least quantitatively. And
therefore maybe that is does not satisfy your vow. I mean it's
more than your vow but it doesn't satisfy because it's fundamentally different.
אימא מודי ליה לרבי, eima modi leh leRabbi, maybe they agree to
רבי that that does not satisfy. ואי איתמר בהא, ve'i itmar beha,
and if the debate was said
about... about the animals, small and big, בהא איכא למימר לרבי, be-ha
ika le-meimar le-Rabbi, that's where Rebbe says you don't fulfill
it because a bigger animal, more אימורין imurin you're actually doing something
different. אבל בהא, aval be-ha, by the case of a מנחה mincha
where no matter big or small it's all one קומץ kometz being
offered, אימא מודו לרבנן, eima modu le-Rabbanan, maybe they would agree to
the Rabbis, צריכא tzricha tells you here that even here he doesn't
agree. But as I said, besides the idea it's all one קומץ,
kometz, it would seem to me that here there's another reason to
say that the Rabbis are right because when you bring X amount,
it's actually it contains within it the smaller amount. A big, a
cow does not, does not have a calf in it, okay? But
ten עשרונות esronot has three עשרונות esronot in it. But so therefore,
but maybe that's exactly the debate, that so maybe I would have
thought Rebbe would have agreed to that and that's why Rebbe is
arguing in our משנה. mishna Bottom line, what we're saying is why
in our משנה mishna. might you require separate ones? Number one, it
starts with the principle that when you say X, you cannot, X
is not a minimum, X is the exact. And number two, some
problem of mixing it, bringing a big amount and say it's mixed
of a נדר and a נדבה, there's some problem with being able
to say that. In principle, you're not allowed to mix it, you
wouldn't be able to offer it on the מזבח, mizbeach, okay,
the amount of oil would not be clear or it would be
different. So those are the reasons that רבי requires each one separate.
All right, let's take a look at the next משנה. mishna הרי
עלי עצים, harei alai etzim, somebody obligates himself to bring wood, and
wood, as we're going to see, you can vow to bring wood
and it's put up on the מזבח. mizbeach. So לא יפחות משני
גזירין, lo yifchot mi-shnei gzirin, it should not be any less than
two logs. All right, if you look, take a look at תוספות
Tosfos says ודוקא כי אמר עצים אבל כי אמר עץ מייתי גזיר
אחד. ve-davka ki amar etzim aval ki amar etz maytei gzir echad.
If you say wood in the singular, one log suffices. All right,
לבונה, levonah, I'm going to bring frankincense, לא יפחות מקומץ, lo yifchot
mi-kometz, a קומץ kometz of לבונה levonah that would be the standard
amount of a לבונה. levonah. חמשה קמצים הם, chamisha kmatzim hem, there
are five קמצים kmatzim and it's easiest to understand this because it's
not really going to mention the standard קומץ kometz of a מנחה
mincha that we're specifically talking about five קמצים kmatzim of לבונה. levonah.
האומר הרי עלי לבונה,
ha-omer harei
alai levonah, לא יפחות מקומץ. lo yifchot mi-kometz. If somebody obligates himself
to bring a לבונה, levonah, minimum is a קומץ. kometz. המנדב מנחה,
ha-menadev mincha, יביא עמה קומץ לבונה, yavi ima kometz levonah, when you
take a מנחה, mincha, you bring with it a קומץ kometz of
לבונה, levonah, right? It doesn't mention the קומץ kometz of the מנחה
Mincha itself. Okay, that's another standard amount of a לבונה levonah on
a מנחה Mincha. is a קומץ. kometz. המעלה את הקומץ בחוץ, ha-ma-aleh
et ha-kometz ba-chutz, if you put up a קומץ kometz of presumably
לבונה levonah outside of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, חייב, chayav, you're
חייב, chayav, okay? שני בזיכין shnei bzichin and the two like spoons
or whatever they were, dishes, for the לחם הפנים, lechem ha-panim, טעונין
שני קמצים, te-unin shnei kmatzim, they each, they get a קומץ kometz
each. So that's five different קמצים kmatzim of לבונה. levonah. תוספות actually
says one of the חידושים chidushim about מעלה בחוץ ma-aleh ba-chutz is
even if you're מעלה ma-aleh one of these two בזיכין bzichin you're
חייב chayav even though it was only half of the total amount.
Fine, so that was a little bit of a digression. הרי עלי
זהב, harei alai zahav, you obligate yourself to bring gold, לא יפחות
מדינר זהב, lo yifchot mi-dinar zahav, not less than one gold
דינר. כסף, dinar kesef לא יפחות מדינר כסף, lo yifchot mi-dinar kesef,
silver, not less than one silver
דינר. dinar. נחשת, nechoshet, לא יפחות ממעה כסף, lo yifchot mi-ma-ah kesef,
a מעה ma-ah of כסף. kesef, So how much is a מעה?
ma-ah? So a דינר זהב dinar zahav is a hundred מעה. ma-ah.
A דינר כסף dinar kesef
is,
excuse me, I got that wrong, a דינר dinar. כסף kesef. is
150 מעה. ma-ah. Let's do it this
way, a דינר זהב dinar zahav is 150 מעה. ma-ah. A דינר
זהב dinar zahav is 25 silver דינרין dinarin and a silver דינר
dinar is six מעה, ma-ah, okay? So if you said that you're
going to bring copper, so it says לא יפחות ממעה כסף, lo
yifchot mi-ma-ah kesef, the amount of copper should be
valued at no less than a silver מעה ma-ah which is a
sixth
of a, of a silver דינר, dinar, okay? So when you say
gold, it's a gold דינר dinar which is worth 25 times a
silver דינר, dinar, when you say silver, it's a silver דינר dinar
which is a silver דינר, dinar, and when you say copper, you
bring copper the value of a sixth of a silver דינר, dinar,
of a מעה. ma-ah. פירשתי ואיני יודע מה פירשתי, perashti ve-eini yode'a
mah perashti. I forgot how much I said, how much gold, how
much silver, how much copper, מביא עד שיאמר לא לכך נתכוונתי, mevi
ad she-yomar lo le-kach nitkavanti, you bring so, as much as you
say I certainly did not mean more than that. All right, so
that makes sense, I hope, that could be very scary. All right,
תנו רבנן, tanu Rabbanan, גמרא, Gemara, the Rabbis taught, קרבן, korban, so
as you know,
it
says ונפש כי תקריב קרבן מנחה, ve-nefesh ki takriv korban mincha, so
the fact that it says the word קרבן korban before it says
the word מנחה, Mincha they learn out that there can be an
additional type of a thing that you bring, מלמד שמתנדבים עצים, melamed
she-mitnadvim etzim, that you can bring wood. I don't exactly get how
they learn it from the פסוק pasuk at five. וכמה? vechama? כמה?
How much? שני גזירים, shenei gezirim, two logs. וכן הוא אומר vechen
hu omer והגורלות הפלנו, vehagoralot hipallnu, now they probably really get it
from this פסוק pasuk in נחמיה Nechemiah והגורלות הפלנו vehagoralot hipellnu or
על קרבן העצים, al korban ha-etzim, like we threw, we cast lots
for the sacrifice of the wood. So there was a way in
which wood itself was being offered up on the מזבח mizbeach and
because it's being called a קרבן, korban, קרבן עצים, korban etzim, so
that we learn out, we read back into this פסוק pasuk by
מנחה Mincha that a קרבן korban you can obligate yourself to bring
עצים. etzim. Okay.
רבי אומר עצים קרבן הם, etzim korban hem, so okay, if they're
saying that the word, based on the word קרבן, korban, then טעונים
מלח, te'unim melach, then you have to put salt on it like
you put salt on everything that's called a קרבן. korban. וטעונים הגשה,
vete'unim hagasha, and you have to touch it to the מזבח, mizbeach,
which is what you do with a מנחה. Mincha, Now you don't
do it with like an עולה, olah, an animal, but again, if
it's similar to anything it's similar to a מנחה because it is,
you know, it's not from something alive, it's from, you know, the
plant world. So you treat it like that, you put salt on
it and then you do a הגשה hagasha to the מזבח. mizbeach.
אמר רבא לדברי רבי עצים טעונים קמיצה. amar Rava le-divrei Rabbi etzim
te'unim kmitza. Heck,
let's go to the next stage and say you do a קמיצה,
kmitza, you have to break them up and take a hand-breath of
it. Now, you know, there's also a מנחה that doesn't need קמיצה,
kmitza, a מנחת חביתין, minchat chavitim,
the מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim, but if you really want to read
it into this פרשה parsha about מנחה, then you should also require
קמיצה. kmitza. And he means it seriously. Okay. אמר רב פפא לדברי
רבי עצים צריכים עצים. amar Rav Pappa le-divrei Rabbi etzim tzrichim etzim.
It's a little reductio ad absurdum. So we're not saying that you're
vowing to dedicate the firewood to the מזבח. mizbeach. You're dedicating it
as a קרבן, korban, as an offering. So if it's an offering,
you have to burn it on the מערכה, ma'aracha, on the fire
pile on the, you know, in the מזבח. mizbeach. So you have
to burn this wood on other wood. So it's a little questionable
whether that's exactly what the משנה Mishna. meant, but that's sort of
where we are taking it. Okay. לבונה, levona, if you say frankincense,
לא יפחות מקומץ. lo yifchos mi-komez. Not less than a hand-breath. מנלן?
minalan? How do you know that you can just dedicate לבונה levona
straight and it gets offered up on the מזבח, mizbeach, and this
is the outer מזבח mizbeach I should say. So אמר דכתיב, amar
de-chtiv, it says, והרים ממנו בקמצו
מסולת המנחה ומשמנה ואת כל הלבונה,
veherim mimenu vekomzo misolet hamincha
umishamnah ve-et
kol halevona, and also all of the לבונה. levona.
מקיש לבונה להרמה דמנחה. maquish levona le-harama de-mincha. So the לבונה levona
is being equated to the קומץ komez of the מנחה itself. מה
הרמה דמנחה קומץ אף לבונה נמי קומץ. mah harama de-mincha komez af
levona nami komez. So that doesn't tell you how do you know,
excuse me, the מנלן minalan wasn't how do you know that you
can dedicate a קומץ, komez, but how do you know that when
you do dedicate לבונה levona it is a קומץ? komez? And that
is because of this פסוק pasuk of והרים ממנו בקמצו veherim mimenu
vekomzo and then ואת כל הלבונה. ve-et kol halevona.
So the לבונה levona is also a קומץ komez and that's true
about a מנחה. There's a debate I'll remind you way, way at
the beginning of this מסכת masechet what happens, it starts as a
קומץ komez on the מנחה but what happens if it's only left
with like one little,
you know, unit, קורט, koret, one little whatever seed or something, you
know, or, or only one or two, is that sufficient or does
it have to have the full amount even בדיעבד? bedieved? So that's
on the מנחה itself. And once we're understanding this idea of a
קומץ komez of a לבונה, levona, we're also understanding that you can
dedicate a לבונה, levona, but where we know that from is not
being spelled out here. Okay. תנו רבנן, הרי עלי למזבח. harei elai
la-mizbeach.
If you say I obligate myself to bring onto the מזבח mizbeach
and you don't say what. So יביא לבונה, yavi levona, then you
have to, you should bring a לבונה, levona, we're going to translate
it as a לבונה. levona. שאין לך דבר שקרב לגבי מזבח אלא
לבונה, she-ein lecha davar she-karav legabei mizbeach ella levona, because you have
nothing that is offered up on the מזבח mizbeach
except לבונה, levona, which is a very bizarre statement. Really? What about
everything else? So we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara we'll see in
a minute. פירשתי ואיני יודע מה פירשתי. I said explicitly I'm going
to offer something on the מזבח mizbeach and I don't remember what.
יביא מכל דבר שקרב לגבי מזבח. yavi mi-kol davar she-karav legabei mizbeach.
Then you have to bring everything, an עולה, olah, a שלמים, shelamim,
a this, a מנחה, whatever, every single possible thing. גוואלד. gevalt. Okay.
So, so let's take a look. ותו לא? v'tu lo? What,
only a לבונה levona is offered up on the מזבח? mizbeach? ואיכא
עולה? ve-ika olah? How about עולה? olah? So the גמרא Gemara says
no, עור לכהנים. or le-kohanim. That the skin goes to the כהנים.
kohanim. So when you said הרי עלי למזבח, harei elai la-mizbeach, we
assume it means to be totally consumed by the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay,
so an עולה olah isn't totally consumed. The כהנים kohanim get the
skin of the animal. ואיכא עולת העוף? ve-ika olat ha-of? How about
עולת העוף? olat ha-of? You throw the whole thing up on the
מזבח. mizbeach. So the גמרא says no, איכא מוראה ונוצה. ika mur'ah
ve-notzah.
The feathers and the, you know, crop or whatever, the gizzard, the
insides, that doesn't go on the מזבח. mizbeach. דף ק"ז עמוד א'.
daf kuf zayin amud alef. ואיכא נסכים? ve-ika nesachim?
How about when you vow for wine? We learned before there that
you can, you know, put that on, just vow wine and that
all goes on the מזבח. mizbeach. לשיתין אזלי. le-shitin azli.
That gets poured into the funnels that go into the cavity under
the מזבח mizbeach and we assume when you said למזבח la-mizbeach you
meant to be burnt on the altar. ואיכא מנחת נסכים? ve-ika minchat
nesachim? How about מנחת נסכים? minchat nesachim?
That that gets fully burnt? Okay. כיון דאיכא מנחה דאכלי כהנים מינה,
Keivan de-ika Mincha de-achli Kohanim minah, לא פסקינא בה. lo paskinah beh.
Yes, it's true, but since there are מנחות that the standard מנחה
is eaten by כהנים, Kohanim, when you say I'm obligating myself for
something that is fully goes on the מזבח Mizbayach or on the,
you know, for something on the מזבח, Mizbayach, when we understand it
means fully on the מזבח, Mizbayach, you're not thinking מנחה. Yes, there
is a type of a מנחה that would satisfy that, but the
מנחה category in your mind is not something that's fully on the
מזבח. Mizbayach. So we translate it as the thing that is only
exists as something that is fully on the מזבח. Mizbayach. Now there
are other things that are not being suggested here. You take a
look at תוספות. ואיכא עולה, Ve-ika Ola, תוספות says bottom of ק"ו
עמוד ב'. kuf vav amud beis. ואם תאמר ואיכא שמן Ve-im tomar
ve-ika shemen למאן דאמר פרק כל התדיר דכליל. le-man de-amar perek kol
ha-tadir de-kalil. How about oil? Right, we had the debate whether you
can offer up just oil. ויש לומר כיון דאיכא שמן דאכלי כהנים
לא פסקי ליה. Ve-yesh lomar keivan de-ika shemen de-achli Kohanim lo paski
leh. Now, the same point, sometimes oil is eaten by the כהנים
Kohanim when it's mixed with the מנחה, so it's not like the
לבונה Levona which only exists as something fully burnt on the מזבח.
Mizbayach. ועוד קשיא ואיכא עצים? Ve-od kasha ve-ika eitzim? How about wood
which we just mentioned? דאפילו לרבי דאמר טעון קמיצה הכל קרב, De-afillu
le-Rabbi de-amar teun kemitza kol kareiv,
even what we just sort of said that you need to take
a קמיצה. kemitza. You take a קמיצה kemitza and then, but you
offer it all up. So anyway, there could have been possible other
things, but לבונה Levona is the classic thing. You know, when people
think, like, burning frankincense on an altar, right? When you say something
to be burnt on the altar, that that is what you mean.
Okay.
But not spelled out here how we even know you can be
מתנדב menadev לבונה, Levona, but focusing more that it's the default in
this case and that the minimum what you mean is a קומץ.
kometz. Let's just finish up to the משנה. הרי עלי זהב לא
יפחות מדינר זהב. Harei alai zahav lo yifchos mi-dinar zahav. ודילמא נסכא?
Ve-dilma naska?
Maybe when you said gold, you did not mean a gold coin.
Maybe you meant, like, a gold, you know, ingot or something, or
bar. אמר רבי אלעזר דאמר מטבע. Amar Rabbi Elazar de-amar matbe'a. You
said it because you said a gold coin. Now, not clear, if
you said a נסכא, naska, would that be small? If you didn't
say coin, would we say what's the minimum size of a gold
ingot? Smaller or greater? תוספות discusses that. ודילמא פריטי? Ve-dilma priti? Maybe
you meant not a major coin, but maybe you meant, like, sort
of like, you know, like the small change of gold, like gold
pennies, I guess. So אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, I'm sorry,
אמר אביי פריטי דדהבא לא עבדי אינשי. Amar Abaye priti de-dahava lo
avdi inshi. No, no, no. People don't make gold pennies. Okay? Gold,
the standard size of a gold coin is, you know, you know,
is a דינר. dinar. כסף לא יפחות מדינר. Kesef lo yifchos mi-dinar.
Even so, even if they exist, it's not what you intended. כסף
לא יפחות מדינר. Kesef lo yifchos mi-dinar. Silver no less than a
silver דינר. dinar. ודילמא נסכא? Ve-dilma naska? Maybe you mean a silver
ingot or a silver bar? אמר רבי אלעזר דאמר מטבע. Amar Rabbi
Elazar de-amar matbe'a. You said a silver coin. ודילמא פריטי? Ve-dilma priti?
Maybe you meant also small change of silver? אמר רב ששת באתרא
דלא סגי פריטי דכספא. Amar Rav Sheshes be-asra lo sagi priti de-kaspa.
In a place where, you know, most people don't use silver small
change, they use, you know, copper coins for small change. Okay? So
here, gold, we just say generally, nobody does it. It's rare and
you would never mean it. Silver, some places yes, some no, so
we're talking in a context, in a scenario in which silver small
change is not prevalent.
All right. נחושת לא יפחות ממעה כסף, Nechoshes lo yifchos mi-ma'ah kesef,
copper should not be worth less than a מעה ma'ah of silver.
So one-sixth of a silver דינר. dinar. תניא רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
אומר לא יפחות מצינורא קטנה של נחושת. Tanya Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
omer lo yifchos mi-tzinnora ketana shel nechoshes. He says, not less than,
like, a type of a fork of copper. למאי חזי? le-mai chazei?
What do you use that for? אמר אביי שמחטטין בו פתילות ומקנחין
בו נרות. Amar Abaye she-mechattin bo pesilos u-mekanchin bo neros. You can
use it, like, you know, to clean out your, your lamp, and
this is not specifically the מנורה, Menorah, תוספות says. Clean out your
lamp and, you know, clean out the wicks. So people would make
a small little, you know, like, I don't know, like a tine
or something of copper. So that's what you mean, because here, copper,
it's interesting, they don't say you mean a copper coin. Why did
all of a sudden we go an amount of copper worth X
value? I mean, they had copper coins. They had, you know, פרוטות.
prutos. But maybe that would be too trivial, but we are interpreting
it so one is a minimum amount of value and here it's,
like, a minimum, the minimum vessel of copper that could be used.
ברזל זה, Barzel zeh, let's say somebody said, you know, iron. תניא
הכי נמי לא יפחות מכילא עורב. Tanya hachi nami lo yifchos mi-kila
orev. The amount of iron to make a spike that would keep
away the ravens. They would put spikes on the top of the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you know, on the roof, that would keep
away the ravens who would be attracted by the smell of the
meat. וכמה? Ve-kamma? אמר רב יוסף אמה על אמה. Amar Rav Yosef
amma al amma. An אמה amma by an אמה amma of iron.
Okay, that's a good amount of iron, whatever, like a foot and
a half. איכא דאמרי לא יפחות מאמה על אמה. Ika de-amri lo
yifchos me-amma al amma. And some have the version not less than
an אמה amma on an אמה. amma. למאי חזי? Le-mai chazei? What
do you use it for? אמר רב יוסף לכילא עורב, Amar Rav
Yosef le-kila orev, for the thing, the spike to keep away the
ravens. Okay, we will end with that.